If you're comparing two quantitative variables to one another,
إذا كنت تقارن بين متغيرين كميين،
say price and sales,
فأشر إلى الأسعار والمبيعات،
or heights and weights,
أو الارتفاعات والأوزان،
the most common plot for such an analysis is the scatter plot.
فإن الرسم الأكثر شيوعًا لمثل هذا التحليل هو الرسم المتفرق.
These plots can be used to visualize
يمكن استخدام هذه الرسومات لتصور
both the strength and the direction of the relationship between the two variables.
قوة العلاقة واتجاهها بين المتغيرين.
This is an example of a strong positive relationship,
هذا مثال على العلاقة الإيجابية القوية،
that is, as one variable increases the other variable also increases.
حيث إنه كلما زاد أحد المتغيرات زاد المتغير الآخر أيضًا.
While this is an example of a strong negative relationship.
في حين أن هذا مثال على العلاقة السلبية القوية.
That is, as one variable increases the other variable decreases.
حيث أنه كلما زاد أحد المتغيرات قل المتغير الآخر.
As the points become more spread out from one another,
عندما تصبح النقاط أكثر ابتعادًا من بعضها البعض،
this weakens the relationship.
يؤدي ذلك إلى إضعاف العلاقة.
So to identify strong or weak relationships,
لذا لتحديد العلاقات القوية أو الضعيفة،
we aren't so much looking at the slope associated with the relationship,
لا ننظر كثير إلى المنحدر المرتبط بالعلاقة،
which is changing here.
والذي يتغير هنا.
These all have the same strength.
كل ذلك له نفس القوة.
But rather, the closeness of the points as we saw before.
لكن بالأحرى، قرب النقاط يزيد من القوة كما رأينا في السابق.
Generally, we consider strength as either weak,
بشكل عام، يتم اعتبار مدى القوة إما ضعيف
moderate or strong, and direction as simply positive or negative.
أو متوسط أو قوي، وتتم الإشارة إلى الاتجاه على اعتبار أنه إما إيجابي أو سلبي.
A numeric value used to capture
تُعرف القيمة الرقمية المستخدمة لالتقاط
these two aspects is known as the correlation coefficient,
هذين الجانبين كمعامل ارتباط،
often just denoted by a lower case r. The correlation coefficient
وغالباً ما تتم الإشارة إليها فقط بالحالة الأقل r. يتم استخدام معامل الارتباط
is used to tell us the strength and the direction of a linear relationship.
لإخبارنا عن بمدى قوة واتجاه العلاقة الخطية.
The correlation coefficient is always between -1 and 1,
يتراوح معامل الارتباط دائمًا بين -1 و1،
where the closer it is to 1 or -1,
حيث يشير الأقرب إلى 1 أو -1،
the stronger the relationship.
كلما كانت العلاقة أقوى.
The negative tells you that there's a negative relationship,
وتشير المؤشرات السلبية إلى وجود علاقة سلبية،
while a positive tells you there's a positive relationship.
في حين تشير المؤشرات الإيجابية إلى وجود علاقة إيجابية.
You will get some practice with this in the quizzes that follow.
ستحصل على بعض الممارسات حول هذه المواضيع في الاختبارات التالية.